so today the book that I want to share
with you that can help you be a better
culture designers this one media virus
by Douglas rushkoff now this book came
out in the early 90s but it's still very
relevant today because it helps us
better understand the way that cultural
patterns can arise from and spread
across media communication systems so
specifically what Doug rushkoff does in
media virus is he explores the way that
ideas can become what are called memes
which is basically structured
information that can spread from one
person to another and then can become
stereotypical stories or behaviors that
go viral or spread the way that a virus
does as an epidemic now in the
biological sense the same can happen
with media information in communications
across the society so one of the things
about this book that is so important for
culture designers is that we need to
understand how perceptions are shaped
and how shared narratives and shared
language are formed within communities
so that we can work with the media
content that is able to spread to help
the ideas that are needed to spread and
succeed so what I love about this book
is that Doug rushkoff takes the approach
of being a technologist and media
analyst so he looks at the way that the
social dimension of new technology can
help shape how information is spread now
the book being written in the 1990s does
use a lot of examples that are a bit
older so it looks at things like the the
beating of rodney king in los angeles
that led to the LA riots and the media
echo chamber that enabled had to happen
how that story kind of took control and
spread in a way that no one quite
understood was going to happen I was
quite surprising when it did or it could
be other things like um he looks at the
Simpsons and other popular pop culture
TV shows that were able to encapsulate
ideas and spread them from one genre to
another and what makes this book so
important for culture designers is that
we really need to understand how media
propagation happens how an idea can get
in
to the cultural space of a discourse and
then rise to prominence or spread widely
enough that it becomes normalized and
then becomes a part of the standard
lexicon of communication now culture
design in many ways is about figuring
out how to spread information more
effectively so that's exactly what this
is about and so for those of you who
want to understand the way that media
content is created and propagated and
how culture itself is actually
constituted by this process of sharing
media information then Doug rush coughs
book the media virus is really a must
read and something that will give you a
lot of theoretical understanding as well
as concrete case study examples of how
to do both the analysis and the design
work so there you go go get media virus
if you want to know how to shape
cultural discourse and the spreading of
ideas